Apiculture (beekeeping) collection
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Apiculture (beekeeping) collection
[after 1898] - [200-]
F-110
Q104890199
1.87 m of textual records 120 photographs 7 film reels
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Financial assistance for the arrangement and description of the records and production of the finding aid was generously provided by Mark Winston, Professor SFU Department Of Biological Sciences (March 2001); the SFU Department Of Biological Sciences (March 2001); and the SFU Faculty Of Science (April 2001).
published
Full
Revised
Title of the collection is based on the contents of the material.
The Apiculture (beekeeping) collection is an artificial grouping of documentary materials relating to the methods, science and culture of beekeeping. The collection was established by the SFU Archives as a complement to its other holdings relating to apiculture, such as the fonds of the British Columbia Honey Producers' Association (F-147), and the papers of SFU faculty member Mark Winston (F-174).
The collection consists of publications, conference proceedings, minutes, correspondence, photographs, and moving images. Material includes government publications, correspondence and registers of provincial beekeepers in British Columbia; published research articles, presentations and reports; course outlines and course material relating to the Bee Masters program and honey judging in British Columbia; photographs of various BC beekeeping activities and personalities; copies of meeting minutes and other records of various beekeeping associations in British Columbia and Canada; moving images featuring beekeeping activities and topics; and various subject files relating to the history of beekeeping in BC.
As an artificial collection, the material had no original order. Arrangement was created by the archivist to facilitate intellectual access and is based on type of document (for publications and special media), provenance (of minutes and correspondence), or subject (for collected materials on various topics and activities).
Due to the volume of records from an accrual added in 2014 (accessions 2012-001 and 2012-042), several sub-series were created by the processing archivist to facilitate intellectual access to the documents in series 1 (Association records), 2 (Educational programs, training, and conferences) and 3 (Government publications, reports, correspondence). A new series 7 (Subject files) was also created. Series 4 (Journals) was deaccessioned in October 2014.
Archives and Records Management Department; Photographic materials; Textual records; Agriculture; Industries; Science and technology
All accessions have been processed as of August 2015. Further accruals are expected.
Material was originally collected and donated to the Archives by a number of individuals, including former British Columbia Provincial Apiarist John Corner; Ministry apicultural specialist John Gates; British Columbia Honey Producers Association members John Boone, Grace Fuhr, and Doug McCutcheon; and SFU faculty member Mark Winston (Department of Biological Sciences). Subsequent accessions were donated to the SFU Archives by the Association's John Boone (between 2007 and 2012), Doug McCutcheon (in 2006, 2008, and 2011), and Mark Winston (2015).
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Files marked "pending review" must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release and, as a result of the review, access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the reference archivist for more details.
Copyright subsists in all or some of the records. Generally, the university is the copyright owner only to works that the donor authored. Please consult the reference archivist for details about the use of copyrighted materials.
- Association records, ca. 1922, 1952 - 2005; F-110-1; 78.5 cm of textual records
  published
  Series primarily comprises copies of records created by a number of associations currently or formerly active in the field of beekeeping. Records consist of association constitutions, meeting minutes, proceedings, newsletters, correspondence, and other documents.
  Series is arranged into 6 sub-series:
  1. British Columbia Commercial Beekeepers Association
  2. Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists
  3. Canadian Beekeepers' Council
  4. Fraser Valley Pollinators' Association
  5. Provincial Apiarists' Association
  6. Other associations
  The arrangement for the series and sub-series was provided by the archivist. Unless otherwise indicated, files are arranged chronologically within each sub-series. As a result of an accrual added in 2014 (accession 2012-001), an additional sub-series was created by the processing archivist to facilitate intellectual access to the documents: F-110-1-6 (Other associations).
  - British Columbia Commercial Beekeepers Association, 1965 - [197-]; F-110-1-1; 2 cm of textual records
    Sub-series primarily comprises copies of records of the annual meetings of the British Columbia Commercial Beekeepers Association. The Association was established around 1962 as an organization of individuals who draw their livelihood primarily from beekeeping or the sale of its products. Its objectives were to promote and develop markets and marketing methods for apiary products, inform members of developments in apiculture research, and participate in the Canadian Beekeepers' Council. The Association appears to have maintained a close relationship with the British Columbia Honey Producers' Association. It disbanded around 1980. Records in this sub-series consist of the Association's constitution, annual meeting minutes, newsletters, and original letterhead.
    Files are arranged chronologically.
    British Columbia Commercial Beekeepers Association
    For related material, see the finding aid for the fonds of the British Columbia Honey Producers' Association (F-147).
    - British Columbia Commercial Beekeepers Association constitution and minutes, 1965 - 1972; F-110-1-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 110-1)
      Textual records
      Pending review
    - British Columbia Commercial Beekeepers Association communications and original letterhead, [197-]; F-110-1-1-02 (Archival box - standard 110-11)
  - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists, 1959 - 2005; F-110-1-2; 68.5 cm of textual records
    Sub-series comprises copies of records of the annual meetings of the Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists. The organization began as the Canadian Association of Apiarists but registered as a professional association in 1975 and changed its name to the current form in that year. It continues as an active organization. The Association promotes cooperation among professional apiculturalists working in agricultural administration, extension or research. Its members generally are employed by federal or provincial governments or universities. The Association maintains a consultative role in relation to the Canadian Honey Council and acts as a liaison with apiculturalists in other countries. Records in this sub-series consist of minutes and proceedings.
    Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturists
    - Canadian Association of Apiculturalists proceedings, 1959; F-110-1-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 110-1)
      Open
    - Canadian Association of Apiculturalists proceedings, 1960; F-110-1-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 110-1)
    - Canadian Association of Apiculturalists proceedings, 1961; F-110-1-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 110-1)
    - Canadian Association of Apiculturalists proceedings, 1962; F-110-1-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 110-1)
    - Canadian Association of Apiculturalists proceedings, 1963; F-110-1-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 110-1)
    - Canadian Association of Apiculturalists proceedings, 1964; F-110-1-2-0-6 (Archival box - standard 110-1)
    - Canadian Association of Apiculturalists proceedings, 1965; F-110-1-2-0-7 (Archival box - standard 110-1)
    - Canadian Association of Apiculturalists proceedings, 1966; F-110-1-2-0-8 (Archival box - standard 110-1)
    - Canadian Association of Apiculturalists proceedings, 1968; F-110-1-2-0-10 (Archival box - standard 110-1)
    - Canadian Association of Apiculturalists proceedings, 1969; F-110-1-2-0-11 (Archival box - standard 110-1)
    - Canadian Association of Apiculturalists proceedings, 1970; F-110-1-2-0-12 (Archival box - standard 110-2)
    - Canadian Association of Apiculturalists proceedings, 1971; F-110-1-2-0-13 (Archival box - standard 110-2)
    - Canadian Association of Apiculturalists proceedings, 1972; F-110-1-2-0-14 (Archival box - standard 110-2)
    - Canadian Association of Apiculturalists proceedings, 1973; F-110-1-2-0-15 (Archival box - standard 110-2)
    - Canadian Association of Apiculturalists proceedings, 1974; F-110-1-2-0-16 (Archival box - standard 110-2)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1975; F-110-1-2-0-17 (Archival box - standard 110-2)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1976; F-110-1-2-0-18 (Archival box - standard 110-2)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1977; F-110-1-2-0-19 (Archival box - standard 110-2)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1978; F-110-1-2-0-20 (Archival box - standard 110-2)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1979; F-110-1-2-0-21 (Archival box - standard 110-2)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1980; F-110-1-2-0-22 (Archival box - standard 110-2)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1981; F-110-1-2-0-23 (Archival box - standard 110-2)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists workshop, 1981; F-110-1-2-0-23.1 (Archival box - standard 110-2)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1982; F-110-1-2-0-24 (Archival box - standard 110-3)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1983; F-110-1-2-0-25 (Archival box - standard 110-3)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1984; F-110-1-2-0-26 (Archival box - standard 110-3)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1985; F-110-1-2-0-27 (Archival box - standard 110-3)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1986; F-110-1-2-0-28 (Archival box - standard 110-3)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1987; F-110-1-2-0-29 (Archival box - standard 110-3)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1988; F-110-1-2-0-30 (Archival box - standard 110-3)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1990; F-110-1-2-0-31 (Archival box - standard 110-4)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1991; F-110-1-2-0-32 (Archival box - standard 110-4)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1992; F-110-1-2-0-33 (Archival box - standard 110-4)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1993; F-110-1-2-0-34 (Archival box - standard 110-4)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1994; F-110-1-2-0-35 (Archival box - standard 110-4)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1995; F-110-1-2-0-36 (Archival box - standard 110-4)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1997; F-110-1-2-0-37 (Archival box - standard 110-4)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1998; F-110-1-2-0-38 (Archival box - standard 110-4)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 1999; F-110-1-2-0-39 (Archival box - standard 110-4)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturalists proceedings, 2000; F-110-1-2-0-40 (Archival box - standard 110-4)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturists - Proceedings 1996 - L'Association canadienne de professionels de l'apiculture, F-110-1-2-0-41 (Archival box - small 110-18)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturists - L'Association canadienne de professionels de l'apiculture - Proceedings 2001, F-110-1-2-0-42 (Archival box - small 110-18)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturists - L'Association canadienne de professionels de l'apiculture - Proceedings 2002, F-110-1-2-0-43 (Archival box - small 110-18)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturists - L'Association canadienne des professionels de l'apiculture - Proceedings 2003, F-110-1-2-0-44 (Archival box - small 110-18)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturists - L'Association canadienne des professionels de l'apiculture - Proceedings 2004, F-110-1-2-0-45 (Archival box - small 110-18)
    - Canadian Association of Professional Apiculturists - L'Association canadienne des professionels de l'apiculture - Proceedings 2005, F-110-1-2-0-46 (Archival box - small 110-18)
  - Canadian Beekeepers' Council, 1957 - 1963; F-110-1-3; 2 cm of textual records
    Sub-series comprises records documenting the activities of the Canadian Beekeepers' Council. The Council was established in 1939 to study problems relating to the marketing of bee products and to promote education and standards. Records consist of correspondence, reports, a pamphlet, and a programme.
    Canadian Beekeepers' Council
    - Canadian Beekeeper's Council, 1957 - 1958; F-110-1-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 110-5)
    - Canadian Beekeeper's Council annual meeting menu and programme, 1963; F-110-1-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 110-11)
  - Fraser Valley Pollinators' Association, 1977 - 1985; F-110-1-4; 1 cm of textual records
    Sub-series comprises copies of records of the meetings of the Fraser Valley Pollinators' Association. The Association was established in 1977 to promote pollination services offered by beekeepers to the growers of various crops, provide high service standards, and negotiate with growers on a group basis. The current status of the Association is not known. Records consist of meeting minutes.
    Fraser Valley Pollinators' Association
    - Fraser Valley Pollinators' Association minutes, 1977 - 1985; F-110-1-4-0-1 (Archival box - standard 110-5)
  - Provincial Apiarists' Association, 1952 - 1959; F-110-1-5; 3 cm of textual records
    Sub-series comprises copies of records of the meetings of the Provincial Apiarists' Association. The Association was established in 1952 as an organization of government apiary officials employed in provincial departments and ministries across Canada. It aimed to promote the scientific and practical efficiency of beekeeping, disseminate progressive ideas relating to apiculture, and secure cooperation among apiculturalists working in the country. The current status of the Association is not known. Records consist of proceedings of the Association's meetings in 1952 and 1958 and a 1959 report.
    Provincial Apiarists' Association
    - Provincial Apiarists' Association proceedings, 1952; F-110-1-5-0-1 (Archival box - standard 110-5)
    - Provincial Apiarists' Association proceedings, 1958; F-110-1-5-0-2 (Archival box - standard 110-5)
    - Provincial Apiarists' Association of Canada, 1959; F-110-1-5-0-3 (Archival box - standard 110-5)
  - Other associations, ca. 1922, 1982 - 1992; F-110-1-6; 2 cm of textual records
    Sub-series comprises records created by other associations currently or formerly active in the field of beekeeping, including the Beekeepers Association of BC, the Surrey Beekeepers Association, and the Vancouver Island Beekeepers' Coalition. Records consist of newsletters, minutes, and other documents.
    Files are arranged alphabetically.
    Beekeepers Association of British Columbia; Surrey Beekeepers Association; Vancouver Island Beekeepers' Coalition; Textual records
    - Beekeepers Association of BC newsletters and flyer, ca. 1922, 1982 - 1987; F-110-1-6-0-1 (Archival box - standard 110-11)
    - Surrey Beekeepers Association newsletters, 1982 - 1992; F-110-1-6-0-2 (Archival box - standard 110-11)
    - Vancouver Island Beekeepers' Coalition minutes, 1987 - 1988; F-110-1-6-0-3 (Archival box - standard 110-11)
- Educational programs, training, and conferences, 1955 - 2003; F-110-2; 20 cm of textual records 1 photograph; Physical description: 1 photograph located in F-110-2-2-0-8
  Series comprises documents relating to apicultural educational programs, training, and conferences. For types of records, see sub-series descriptions.
  Series is arranged into 3 sub-series:
  1. General
  2. Bee Masters Program
  3. Honey judging
  The arrangement for the series and sub-series was provided by the archivist. Files are arranged chronologically within each sub-series. As a result of an accrual added in 2014 (accession 2012-001), an additional sub-series was created by the processing archivist to facilitate intellectual access to the documents: F-110-2-3 (Honey judging).
  - General, 1962 - 1963, 1988, 1999 - 2001; F-110-2-1; 3 cm of textual records
    Sub-series comprises material relating to miscellaneous apicultural educational programs, training, and conferences. Documents consist of course material, proceedings, correspondence, reports and notes.
    - Science in Agriculture night school course, 1962 - 1963; F-110-2-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 110-5)
    - Proceedings of the Pacific Northwest Apitherapy conference, 1988; F-110-2-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 110-11)
    - Beekeeping exhibit trailer - Armstrong Interprovincial Exhibition, 1999 - 2001; F-110-2-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 110-11)
  - Bee Masters Program, 1955 - 2003; F-110-2-2; 12 cm of textual records 1 photograph
    Sub-series comprises material relating to the Bee Masters program. Bee Masters is an intensive course in advanced beekeeping sponsored by the British Columbia ministry responsible for agriculture. The first course was held in 1955. Since around 1986, it has been held at Simon Fraser University and offered jointly by the BC government and SFU's Department of Biological Sciences. Early courses were lengthier to include a field trip to a beekeeping location, while later courses dropped the field trip component and thus shortened to five days in length. Documents include the first written examinations from 1955 and 1958, course outlines, lectures, articles, participant and speakers lists, evaluations, forms, correspondence, pamphlets, and other course material.
    - Bee Masters course material, 1955 - 1993; F-110-2-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 110-5)
    - Bee Masters certificates, 1966; F-110-2-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 110-5)
    - Bee Masters course material, 1986; F-110-2-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 110-5)
    - Bee Masters course material, 1989; F-110-2-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 110-5)
    - Bee Masters course material, 1990; F-110-2-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 110-5)
    - Bee Masters course material, 1992; F-110-2-2-0-6 (Archival box - standard 110-6)
    - Bee Masters course material, 1993; F-110-2-2-0-7 (Archival box - standard 110-6)
    - Bee Masters course material, 1994; F-110-2-2-0-8 (Archival box - standard 110-6)
      Textual records; Photographic materials
    - Bee Masters course material, 1996; F-110-2-2-0-9 (Archival box - standard 110-6)
    - Bee Masters short course material, 1962 - 2003; F-110-2-2-0-10 (Archival box - standard 110-11)
    - Bee Masters short course material and pamphlet, 1964 - 1966; F-110-2-2-0-11 (Archival box - standard 110-11)
      Open, no restrictions
      Access review (Apr 14, 2023) – File is open, no restricted information identified.
    - Bee Masters short course material, 2003; F-110-2-2-0-12 (Archival box - standard 110-11)
  - Honey judging, 1966 - 2001; F-110-2-3; 5 cm of textual records
    Sub-series comprises originals and copies of material relating to the history of honey judging and the courses developed to train honey judges in British Columbia. The need for honey judges grew out of the desire to promote honey and its uses at various exhibitions in BC, and in particular the Pacific National Exhibition at Vancouver and the Interior Provincial Exhibition at Armstrong. As early as the 1920s, a score card was developed to rank honey on a standardized scale and was used into the 1950s. The Canadian Beekeepers Council, established in the 1940s, also developed a score card allowing for the judging of honey at a national level. By the mid-1960s in BC, there was a demand for formally-trained honey judges, and a one day course was held in 1966 to teach, test, and certify the first group. Additional courses followed in 1975 and the 1980s. Certified honey judges continue to be an important part of exhibitions. Records include course materials, forms, notes, scoring sheets, correspondence, and other documents.
    - Honey judging course materials and PNE participation, 1966 - 2001; F-110-2-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 110-11)
    - Honey Judging School to Train Honey Judges - Vernon, 1975; F-110-2-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 110-11)
    - Score sheets for judging honey and pollen, 1975, 2001; F-110-2-3-0-3 (Archival box - standard 110-11)
    - Lists of certified honey judges, 1983 - 1992; F-110-2-3-0-4 (Archival box - standard 110-11)
    - Honey judging course - instructor's teaching materials and notes, [ca. 1985]; F-110-2-3-0-5 (Archival box - standard 110-11)
    - Honey judging course - teaching materials, [ca. 2001]; F-110-2-3-0-6 (Archival box - standard 110-11)
- Government publications, reports, correspondence, 1915 - 1997; F-110-3; 67 cm of textual records 2 photographs
  Series comprises publications, reports and correspondence of government departments and programs responsible for apiculture in their jurisdiction. Government departments represented primarily include the Department or Ministry of Agriculture for British Columbia, but also Canada, Ontario, and the United States. For types of records, see sub-series descriptions.
  1. British Columbia - beekeeper registers
  2. British Columbia - correspondence
  3. British Columbia - newsletters
  4. British Columbia - publications and forms
  5. British Columbia - reports
  6. Other governments
  The arrangement for the series and sub-series was provided by the archivist. Due to the volume of records from an accrual added in 2014 (accessions 2012-001 and 2012-042), six sub-series were created by the processing archivist to facilitate intellectual access to the documents: F-110-3-1 through F-110-3-6. The new sub-series were arranged alphabetically. The original and accrual files were then chronologically integrated into the new sub-series, with the exception of the final sub-series which is arranged alphabetically.
  2 photographs located in F-110-3-5-0-1
  - British Columbia - beekeeper registers, 1929 - 1943, 1958 - 1968; F-110-3-1; 11 cm of textual records
    Sub-series comprises beekeeper registers and lists showing names, addresses, location, district and number of hives maintained in BC and specific districts.
    - British Columbia Department of Agriculture - register of British Columbia beekeepers, 1929 - 1943; F-110-3-1-0-1; F-110-3-0-0-4 (Newspaper box 110-10)
    - List of beekeepers - South Okanagan area, 1958; F-110-3-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 110-12)
    - List of beekeepers - Interior District, 1966; F-110-3-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 110-12)
    - Interior beekeepers, 1968; F-110-3-1-0-4 (Archival box - standard 110-12)
  - British Columbia - correspondence, 1958 - 1983; F-110-3-2; 8 cm of textual records